Richard D. Sparks papers, 1925-1962
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Richard D. Sparks gorillas papers, 1925-1962
MS 093
Richard D. Sparks
Chiefly correspondence between Richard Sparks and a variety of people, mainly from the 1930s, about the proper treatment of gorillas. Of particular concern is the well-being of three gorillas named Ngagi, Mbongo, and Okere. Sparks advocated for their scientific study in a zoo, instead of their becoming a circus sideshow.
.4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Richard D. Sparks was a treasurer of Sparks Milling Company, Alton, Illinois, and an animal rights advocate for gorillas.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series
Series I: Correspondence, 1925-1962 (bulk 1931-1932)
Series II: Photographs,
Series III: Magazines and reprints, 1926-1950
Scope and Content Note
Chiefly correspondence between Richard Sparks and a variety of people, mainly from the 1930s, about the proper treatment of gorillas. Of particular concern is the well-being of Ngagi, Mbongo, and Okere, captured by author Martin Johnson in the Belgian Congo, in 1931. Sparks advocates for their scientific study in a zoo rather than becoming a circus sideshow. Chief correspondents are: Mary L. Jobe Akeley, naturalist associated with the American Museum of Natural History; Belle J. Benchley, manager of the Zoological Society of San Diego; and Harold C. Bingham, psychobiologist in the study of gorilla behavior. Other correspondence, magazine articles, and black-and-white photographs are concerned with Congo, a gorilla brought from the Belgian Congo in 1925 by author Ben Burbridge, and studied by Yale University researcher Robert M. Yerkes. Miscellaneous material relates to Carl Akeley's animal sculptures, Theodore Spicer-Simson's medallic art, and other gorillas in captivity.
Akeley, Carl Ethan, 1864-1926.; Akeley, Mary L. Jobe (Mary Lenore Jobe), 1878-1966 -- Correspondence.; Benchley, Belle Jennings, 1882- -- Correspondence.; Bingham, Harold Clyde, b. 1888 -- Correspondence.; Burbridge, Benjamin, b. 1880.; Johnson, Martin, 1884-1937.; Spicer-Simson, Theodore.; Yerkes, Robert Mearns, 1876-1956.; Ngagi (Gorilla); Mbongo (Gorilla); Congo (Gorilla); Gorilla -- Photographs.; Wild animal collecting -- Congo (Democratic Republic); American Museum of Natural History.; Zoological Society of San Diego.; Wild animal parks
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1925-1962
  - Akeley, Carl 1925-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Akeley, Mary L. Jobe 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Benchley, Belle J. 1931-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bingham, Harold C. 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Burbridge, Benjamin 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Detwiler, Samuel R. 1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Johnson, Martin 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - MacCreagh, Gordon 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Merriam, John C. 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Spicer-Simson, Theodore 1947-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Yerkes, Robert M. 1931-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Various 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Photographs
  - Photographs of Gorillas (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series III: Magazines and reprints, 1926-1950
  - Richard D. Sparks, "Congo - A Personality." (Article in Field & Stream) January 1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Articles, reprints, and clippings about gorillas 1926-1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)